Guide to the Marvin Leiner Papers TAM.607
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
Marvin Leiner Papers
Bulk, 1963-1979
circa 1963-2005
TAM.607
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
43.5 linear feet in 43 record cartons and 1 small flat box
Marvin Leiner is a scholar of Cuban education and the author of several books on educational reforms in the wake of the Cuban Revolution. The collection primarily consists of research Leiner conducted while living in Cuba during the 1968-1969 school year and during his many return visits in the 1970s and 1980s.
Leiner, Marvin
Historical/Biographical Note
Marvin Leiner is the author of several books on sexual politics and education/childcare in Cuba. Much of his research comes from interviews he conducted and diaries he kept while living in Cuba for the 1968-1969 school year and subsequent trips he made in the 1970s and 1980s. Leiner taught for many years in the Bedford Stuyvesant and Bushwick sections of Brooklyn. He has a Ph.D. in Elementary Education from New York University, and he has lectured in Latin American Studies at Yale and was a Fellow of Yale's Trumbull College.
Leiner's best known book, Sexual Politics in Cuba: Machismo, Homosexuality, and AIDS, analyzes the Cuban practice of quarantining individuals with HIV in the context of the Cuban Revolution. The book also examines the social and educational effects of the Cuban government's intolerance of homosexuality and the efforts by Cuban educators to introduce sex education in schools. Leiner's research interests also include other education reforms in the wake of the Cuban Revolution, particularly the Escuela al Campo (School to the Countryside) program, which incorporated literacy, sports, and cultural programs into agricultural work in the countryside. His other works on the topic of education include Children Are the Revolution: Daycare in Cuba and Children of the Cities: Education of the Powerless, which he edited. Leiner is a Professor Emeritus of Education at Queens College, City University of New York.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Researchers interested in using audiovisual materials in this collection (films, cassette tapes, VHS tapes, et cetera) must use a digitized copy, which we refer to as an access copy. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that already have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room; materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. These requests are free of charge and can be made in anticipation of your visit. The process typically takes four to six weeks. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A librarian will respond to you with further information.
Separated Materials
Approximately 5.5 linear feet of books and periodicals on Cuban politics, gender issues, education, and healthcare were separated for library cataloging. Some personal papers and photographs were returned to the donor.
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains Marvin Leiner's extensive research on Cuban education, sexual politics, and health care, conducted in the late 1960s through the 1990s. His research materials consist of of reel-to-reel audio tapes, cassette tapes, slides, photographs, film, diaries, field notes from school visits, and transcripts of interviews with Cuban educators, psychologists, administrators from the Ministry of Education, and other professionals. The collection also contains files from Leiner's speaking engagements and early working manuscripts of his published works. To a much lesser extent, the collection also includes Leiner's research on education and literacy programs in China and Nicaragua.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Gift of Marvin Leiner, 2012. The accession number associated with this donation is 2012.018
Bravo, Ernesto; Bravo, Estela; Leiner, Marvin; Cuba |x History |y Revolution, 1959.; Cuba |x Social conditions.; Diaries.; Education |z China.; Education |z Cuba.; Education |z Nicaragua.; Interviews.; Public health |z Cuba.; Research (document genres).; Sex role |z Cuba.
- Box 1, 1963-1982
  Scope and Content Note
  Cuba Trips: Interviews, Notes, Curriculum, and Cuban Press on Education Issues
- Box 2, 1968-1983
  Cuba Trips: Escuela al Campo, Interviews, Notes, Exams and Curriculum
- Box 3, 1968-early 1970s
  Cuba Trips: Escuela al Campo, Preschools, Interviews, Notes, and Teacher Training
- Box 4, 1968-early 1970s
  Cuba Trips: Interviews and Interdisciplinary Seminar on Permanent Education
- Box 5, 1968-1980s
  Cuba Trips: Escuela al Campo, Copies of Fidel Castro Speeches, Interviews, and Research on Cuban Education and Economy
- Box 6, 1970s-1983
  Cuba Trips: Interviews with Teachers and Administrators
- Box 7, 1968-1969, 1983-1984, 1990s-2003
  Cuba Trips: Interviews (many with Ministry of Education)
  Subject Files on Cuban Education, Gay Rights, Elian Gonzalez, Economy, and Health Care
- Box 8, 1969-early 1970s, 1990s
  Cuban Literacy Campaign
  Helms-Burton Conference (1997)
  Children Are the Revolution Working Appendix
  Cuba Trips: Escuela al Campo, Interviews, and Notes and Diaries
- Box 9, 1980s
  Nicaragua Literacy Crusade (Field Notes and Interviews)
  Cuba: Gay Rights/Sex Education and Interviews with Educators
  China Trip: Notes on Education
- Box 10, late 1960s-early 1970s
  Cuba Trips: Student Work ("Five Wishes" Compositions) and Notes on Infant Circles, Escuela al Campo, Mimica Teaching Method, and Education in Ciudad Libertad
- Box 11, late 1960s-1986
  Cuba Trips: School Field Notes and Interviews, Notes, and Research re: Sex Education, Educational Psychology, and Quality of Education in Cuba
- Box 12, late 1960s-1984
  Speeches on Status of Cuban Education
  Cuba Trips: Diary (1971 Trip), Field Notes, Escuela al Campo, and Daycare Research
- Box 13, late 1960s-early 1980s
  Correspondence and Publicity re: Leiner's Publications
  Cuba Trips: Diaries (1980s), Interviews, Field Notes, and Photographs
- Box 14, 1969-late 1980s
  Children of the Cities Manuscript
  Grant Information and Correspondence
  Cuba Trips: Escuela al Campo, Mimica, Karen Leiner's Diary, and Jardin Infantil
- Box 15, 1969-early 1980s
  Early Manuscript of Day Care in Cuba
  Notes and Speaking Files from Conferences on Cuba
- Box 16, late 1960s-1980s, 2000s
  Leiner's Field Notes
  Curriculum and Teaching Training
  1986 Pedagogy Conference in Havana
- Box 17, late 1960s-1988
  Programs and Abstracts from Various Conferences re: Public Health and Education in Cuba
  Photographs and Field Notes from Cuba Trips
  Cuban Ministry of Education Reports
- Box 18, 1980s-early 2000s
  Drafts of Sexual Politics in Cuba
  Speaking Files from Townsend Harris High School Founder's Day
  Conference Papers
  Subject Files re: HIV and Education in Cuba
- Box 19, late 1960s-1990s
  Student Work
  Photographs from Cuban Daycare Centers
  Subject Files re: Literacy/Education and AIDS in Cuba
- Box 20, 1980-early 2000s
  Speaking Files and Subject Files re: Literacy/Education, Sex Education and AIDS, and Women in Cuba
  Nicaragua: Literacy Campaign and Field Notes from 1980 Trip
- Box 21, 1960s, 1980s, undated
  Cuban Education Pamphlets
  Cuba Trips: Interviews and Escuela al Campo
- Box 22, 1950s-1990s
  Reports and Conference Materials re: Cuban Education, Cuban Economy, and Rural Youth in Developing Countries
  Cuba Trips: Interviews, Escuela al Campo, and Elementary Education
- Box 23, 1968-1980s
  Photographs, Negatives, and Slides from Cuba and Other Locations
  Interviews re: Cuban Education
- Box 24, late 1960s-1980s
  Nicaragua Literacy Campaign
  Cuban Filmmaking (Research and Events)
  Cuba Trips: Interviews and Research re: Educational Psychology, Physical Education, Special Education, and Literacy Campaigns
- Box 25, late 1960s-1980s
  Cuba Trips: Kenny Leiner's School Notes
  Interviews and Research re: Cuban Education (especially Cuban Literacy Campaign, Rural Education, and Círculos Infantiles) and Revolutionary Ideology
- Box 27, undated
  Research Files (Bibliography of Sources on Index Cards)
- Box 28, circa 1960-1969
  Oversize Children's Art
- Boxes 29-44 (Box 29-44)
  Audiovisual material